The RNN shown here has been trained to translate from English to Spanish
The input sentence is "I Eat Apples".
Constructing the encoder's hidden units
Constructing the decoder's hidden units
The attention vector is calculated
Attention uses the previous decoder unit
The attention vector provides a weight for each of the encoder's units
These weights are used to calculate the context vector
The context vector tells the decoder which hidden units to pay attention to
The context vector gives "I" a weight of 0.12, "Eat" a weight of 0.88, and "Apples" a weight of 0.00
The context vector is telling the decoder to pay the most attention to "Eat"
Using the context vector, the decoder unit is able to determine what to translate
It decides to translate the word "Eat" conjugated for the pronoun "I"
This results in the Spanish word "Como"
The same process is then repeated but for the second decoder unit
The attention vector gives "Apples" a weight of 0.99
The context vector is paying the most attention to "Apples"
The decoder decides to translate the word "Apples" into Spanish
This results in the Spanish word "Manzanas"